# Brian Johns

DATA ANALYST
DATA SCIENTIST

Email: the.brian.johns@gmail.com

Phone: 778-991-2482

Website: swimmingindata.com

LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/thebrianjohns

Github: github.com/thebrianjohns

#### **PROFILE**

3-Time Canadian Olympic swimmer who understands the work ethic and determination needed to achieve excellence.

Experienced coach and leader who can take a wealth of knowledge and communicate effectively to stakeholders, teammates and co-workers.

A life-long student who has always used an analytical mindset in order to gain unique insights, find new ways to solve problems and learn new skills.

#### **SKILLS**

#### Languages:

• Python, SQL, R

## Data Analysis:

NumPy, Pandas, PySpark, SciPy

## Data Visualization:

• Tableau, Holistics, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Plotly

## Statistics:

Hypothesis Testing, A/B Testing

# Machine Learning:

• Scikit-Learn, Keras, TensorFlow, PyTorch

## Big Data:

- AWS, Hadoop, Spark, Hive, SageMaker
- Github and Command Line

## **EXPERIENCE**

# Head of Coaching Science | FORM

OCT 2022 - PRESENT, VANCOUVER, BC

Served as an expert advisor to provide my swimming and coaching domain expertise across all departments within the company.

Developed models using Holistics with the Analytics team to show the efficacy of our training programs and help define the KPI's for our user's performance.

Worked with a multidisciplinary team in order to deliver data-driven content that evaluated our users, provided programming and tracked long-term improvement

## Teacher's Assistant - Data Science | BrainStation

APR 2022 - JUL 2022, VANCOUVER, BC

Selected as a Teacher's Assistant based on my academic performance and communication skills when enrolled at BrainStation.

Evaluated and mentored students on topics such as SQL, Tableau, ML and Big Data analysis.

Taught supplementary material to enhance student's understanding of using Python, ML Models and Big Data tools.

# Director of Swimming/Head Coach | Vancouver Pacific Swim Club

SEP 2016 - OCT 2021, VANCOUVER, BC

Implemented training programs to holistically develop our swimmers to achieve their daily and long-term goals.

Collaborated with a variety of stakeholders, such as parents, coaches, board members and rental facilities, in order to deliver our programming and meet financial expectations, particularly through the pandemic

# **PROJECTS**

## **Predicting & Evaluating NHL Salaries**

JAN - APR 2022, BrainStation

Utilized NHL basic and advanced statistics to predict and evaluate NHL player's salaries by using Linear Regression, XGBoost, Random Forest and Clustering models.

# **Analyzing Car Accidents in Vancouver Neighborhoods**

**JULY 2022** 

Collected data from ICBC and the City of Vancouver and used MySQL to conduct advanced data analysis, such as window functions and common table expressions, and developed data visualizations and dashboards through Tableau.

## **Sentiment Analysis on Dallas Mavericks Tweets**

MAY 2023

Used data from Twitter and NBA games to perform Sentiment Analysis on Dallas Mavericks tweets using NLP, SMOTE, and Logistic Regression and Naive Bayes models for multinomial classification.

## **EDUCATION**

## BrainStation | Diploma, Data Science

JAN 2022 - APR 2022, VANCOUVER, BC, CANADA

University of British Columbia | Master's in Kinesiology, Coaching Science

SEP 2009 - APR 2011, VANCOUVER, BC, CANADA

University of British Columbia | Bachelor's in Human Kinetics, Phys Ed

JAN 2001 - APR 2009, VANCOUVER, BC, CANADA